Guide to the Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program Records 2006-2016
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program Records
2006-2016
Oregon Century Farm & Ranch Program.
MSS ORCFRP
5.00 cubic feet, including 220 photographs, and 542 Kbytes database 13 boxes, including 1 oversize box
Special Collections and Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/findingaids
The Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program Records document farms and ranches in Oregon that have applied for and received recognition as Century or Sesquicentennial farms or ranches. The records consist primarily of application materials and administrative files related to the awards ceremonies; a database listing all the farms and ranches accepted into the program is also included. The Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program was established in 1958. All available application files and select administrative files are digitized and available in Oregon Digital.
Historical Note:
The Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program began in 1958, just prior to the celebration of Oregon's statehood centennial in 1959, to honor farm and ranch families with century-long connections to the land and to recognize Oregon's rich agricultural heritage. The program introduced a Sesquicentennial Award in 2008, on the eve of Oregon's 150th anniversary. As of 2015, 1,175 families have received the Century designation and 33 families have been honored with the Sequicentennial award.
The Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program is administered by the Oregon Agricultural Education Foundation and is supported in part by a partnership of the Oregon Farm Bureau, the State Historic Preservation Department, the Oregon Department of Agriculture, the Oregon Historical Society, and the Oregon Travel Information Council.
Oregon Century Farm & Ranch Program.; Oregon Farm Bureau.
Born digital.; Photographic prints.
Agriculture--Oregon.; Century farms--Oregon.; Family farms.
Agriculture; Home and Family; Ranching; Oregon; Electronic Records; Photographs
The records for 2006 to 2010 were donated by the Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program in 2011. Additional records were donated annually.
Additions to the collection are expected annually.
The Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program Records are available for research.
The OSU Memorabilia Collection (MSS MC) includes additional materials pertaining to the Century Farm and Ranch Program. The OSU Special Collections and Archives Research Center holdings include a number of extensive collections documenting Oregon agriculture and farms and ranches throughout the state. Pre-2006 application files and administrative records of the program are held by the Oregon Historical Society.
The collection is arranged as three series: Series 1 - Century Farm and Ranch Application Files, 2006-2015, Series 2 - Sesquicentennial Farm and Ranch Application Files, 2008-2015, and Series 3 - Administrative Materials and Awards Ceremonies, 2006-2015. Application files in Series 1 and 2 are arranged in chronological order by CFR (Century Farm and Ranch) or SFR (Sesquicentennial Farm and Ranch) number.
The Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program Records document the recognition of Oregon family farms and ranches that have been been operated continuously by a family for a century or more. The records consist primarily of application materials for each farm or ranch. The application files from 1958-2005 and administrative records from those years are held by the Oregon Historical Society. This collection contains records from 2006 to the present. Additional records will be added to the collection on an annual basis. The application materials include completed forms, correspondence, photographs, DVDs, published narratives, maps, and copies of historical documentation of land ownership. The collection also includes admisinstrative materials, primarily from award ceremonies and lists of farms and ranches that received Century or Sesquicentennial designation from 2006 to present.
The records include more than 220 photographs submitted with applications; most of these images are duplicates of original historical photographs of the farms and ranches. Some of the photographs are contemporary images of farm structures and family members. Color and b/w prints are included. Several of the applications also include copies of digital image files on CD or flash drive.
Materials from the ORCFRP awards presentation program are represented and consist of program brochures and outlines, descriptions of the farms inducted, contact information for the awardees, ORCFRP newsletters, and a printed copy of the presentation. Also included is a copy of the book "Eating It Up in Eden: The Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Cookbook" by Richard Engeman.
The collection also includes a database (in electronic form) listing all the farms and ranches that have been accepted into the program since its inception in 1958. The database includes the historic and current acreage of the property, structures currently residing on the property, the economic use of the farm or ranch, and whether the property was part of a donation land claim. An online database is hosted by the Oregon Explorer.
- Century Farm and Ranch Application Files, 2006-2016; Series 1
  Series 1 consists of Oregon Century Farm and Ranch applications for the years 2006 through present. Applications and supporting materials such as property records and family history documents are submitted to the Century Farm and Ranch Program, part of the Oregon Farm Bureau, for recognition of family owning and working the same land for one hundred years or more. Each application and supporting materials are individually foldered. Application files in Series 1 are arranged in chronological order by CFR (Century Farm and Ranch) number. Two exceptions are CFR 1150 and CFR 1151. The original application for CFR 1150 began in 2007 and was approved in 2010. The original application for CFR 1151 began in 2006 and was approved in 2010.
  - CFR 1106 Bruck, Vernon, 2006 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - CFR 1107 Doherty, Agnes, 2006 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - CFR 1108 Elliot, Lila and Jim, 2006 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - CFR 1109 Follett, Boyd and Sherree, 2006 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - CFR 1110 McGhehey, John and Patricia, 2006 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - CFR 1111 Mahaffy Tree Farm Inc., 2006 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - CFR1112 Morin, Wayne, 2006 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - CFR 1113 Olson, Wilbur, 2006 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - CFR 1114 Pambrun, F. Samuel, 2006 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - CFR 1115 Skinner, Barbara and Fery, Carol, 2006 (Box-folder 1.01)
  - CFR 1116 Smock, Donell and Mary, 2006 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - CFR 1117 Unger Enterprises, 2006 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - CFR 1118 Wettlaufer, Irv, Joan and Edith, 2006 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - CFR 1119 Chambers, Wayne and David and Graffenberger, Marilyn, 2006 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - CFR 1120 Charpilloz, Kathleen and Hanson, Lisa, 2007 (Box-folder 1.15)
  - CFR 1121 Duyck, Dorothy, 2007 (Box-folder 1.16)
  - CFR 1122 Powell, Donald, 2007 (Box-folder 1.17)
  - CFR 1123 Larson, Carl, 2007 (Box-folder 1.18)
  - CFR 1124 Gray, Brett, 2007 (Box-folder 1.19)
  - CFR 1125 Avalon Orchards, 2008 (Box-folder 1.02)
  - CFR 1126 Campbell, Marjorie, 2008 (Box-folder 1.21)
  - CFR 1127 Parsons, Judson - Cogswell, LTD - Hillcrest Orchard, Hillcrest Orchard; 2008 (Box-folder 1.22)
  - CFR 1128 Hafner, Walter, 2008 (Box-folder 1.23)
  - CFR 1129 Hellberg, Leland, 2008 (Box-folder 1.24)
  - CFR 1130 Peter, Ernest, 2008 (Box-folder 1.25)
  - CFR 1131 Jaeger, Henry and William, 2009 (Box-folder 2.1)
  - CFR 1132 Dement Ranch, 2009 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - CFR 1133 Gilbert, Steve, 2009 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - CFR 1134 Bartels, Larry and Sheri, 2009 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - CFR 1135 Van Horn Vineyards, 2009 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - CFR 1136 Carleton, Helen, 2009 (Box-folder 2.6)
  - CFR 1137 Ek, Glen, 2009 (Box-folder 2.7)
  - CFR 1138 Brady, Marie, 2009 (Box-folder 2.8)
  - CFR 1139 Greiner, James, 2009 (Box-folder 2.9)
  - CFR 1140 Hoffman, Robert, 2009 (Box-folder 2.01)
  - CFR 1141 Knox, Doris, 2009 (Box-folder 2.11)
  - CFR 1142 Obersinner, Leonard and Carol, 2009 (Box-folder 2.12)
  - CFR 1143 Peters, Don and Ann, 2009 (Box-folder 2.13)
  - CFR 1144 Schlechter, James, 2009 (Box-folder 2.14)
  - CFR 1145 Shelburne, Robert and Sharon, 2009 (Box-folder 2.15)
  - CFR 1146 Sowa, Timothy and Mary, 2009 (Box-folder 2.16)
  - CFR 1147 Peterson, Herbert, 2009 (Box-folder 2.17)
  - CFR 1148 Byron Scott Farms Inc., Jenks, 2009 (Box-folder 2.18)
  - CFR 1149 Byron Scott Farms Inc., Knighton, 2009 (Box-folder 2.19)
  - CFR 1150 Fosberg, Arlene, 2007 (approved 2010) (Box-folder 3.1)
  - CFR 1151 Bangs, Larry and Paula, 2006 (approved 2010) (Box-folder 3.2)
  - CFR 1152 Charpilloz, Jeffrey and Stacy, 2010 (Box-folder 3.3)
  - CFR 1153 Cherry, Helen, 2010 (Box-folder 3.4)
  - CFR 1154 Cruickshank, Gary and Barbara, 2010 (Box-folder 3.5)
  - CFR 1155 Duyck, Tom and Vickie, 2010 (Box-folder 3.6)
  - CFR 1156 Edwards, Jasper and Marie, 2010 (Box-folder 3.7)
  - CFR 1157 Fiala, Wes, Doug, Anne, Richard and Art, 2010 (Box-folder 3.8)
  - CFR 1158 Gutoski, Peter and Judy, 2010 (Box-folder 3.9)
  - CFR 1159 Hentze, Alice, 2010 (Box-folder 3.01)
  - CFR 1160 Harnisch, David and Esther, 2010 (Box-folder 3.11)
  - CFR 1161 Hollingsworth, John and Adair, 2010 (Box-folder 3.12)
  - CFR 1162 Leighty, Glenn, Sharon and Ron, 2010 (Box-folder 3.13)
  - CFR 1163 Santoro, Joe, Lena and Eleanor, 2010 (Box-folder 3.14)
  - CFR 1164 Schwartz, Allen and Susan, 2010 (Box-folder 3.15)
  - CFR 1165 Silbernagel, Paul, 2010 (Box-folder 3.16)
  - CFR 1166 Smutz, Lawrence and Barbara, 2010 (Box-folder 3.17)
  - CFR 1167 Werth, Dennis and Elmer, 2010 (Box-folder 3.18)
  - CFR 1168 Bierly, Evelyn, 2011 (Box-folder 4.1)
  - CFR 1169 Brown, Anna Belle, 2011 (Box-folder 4.2)
  - CFR 1170 Cantrell, Howard, 2011 (Box-folder 4.3)
  - CFR 1171 Flowers, Robert and Christy, 2011 (Box-folder 4.4)
  - CFR 1172 Langdon, James, 2011 (Box-folder 4.5)
  - CFR 1173 Delbert Langdon Farm, 2011 (Box-folder 4.6)
  - CFR 1174 Rocky Knoll, LLC - Carpenter Family Farm, Rocky Knoll, LLC - Carpenter Family Farm; 2011 (Box-folder 4.7)
  - CFR 1175 Rhode, Glen, 2011 (Box-folder 4.8)
  - CFR 1176 Woods, Ruth, 2011 (Box-folder 4.9)
  - CFR 1177 Yamhill Soil and Water Conservation District, 2011 (Box-folder 4.01)
  - CFR 1178 Morgan, Brenda and Baldwin, James, 2012 (Box-folder 5.1)
  - CFR 1179 Leavy, Edward, 2012 (Box-folder 5.2)
  - CFR 1180 Hiebenthal, David and Kari, 2012 (Box-folder 5.3)
  - CFR 1181 Defrees, Albert, 2012 (Box-folder 5.4)
  - CFR 1182 Sly, James and Barbara Jo, 2012 (Box-folder 5.5)
  - CFR 1183 Walkey, Mark, 2012 (Box-folder 5.6)
  - CFR 1184 Balin Farm Trust, 2012 (Box-folder 5.7)
  - CFR 1185 Kerns, Earl, 2012 (Box-folder 5.8)
  - CFR 1186 Schierling Family Trust, 2012 (Box-folder 5.9)
  - CFR 1187 Fanning, Milton and Delores, 2012 (Box-folder 5.01)
  - CFR 1188 Kalander, John and Sandra, 2012 (Box-folder 5.11)
  - CFR 1189 Gerber, Carrie Wheeler, 2012 (Box-folder 5.12)
  - CFR 1190 Payne, Mark and Kellene, 2012 (Box-folder 5.13)
  - CFR 1191 Livingston, Sharon, 2012 (Box-folder 5.14)
  - CFR 1192 Bodnar, John, 2012 (Box-folder 5.15)
  - CFR 1193 Strubhar, Maxine, 2012 (Box-folder 5.16)
  - CFR 1196 Buchanan, Cheryl and Bunch, Rod and Susan, 2013 (Box-folder 6.1)
  - CFR 1197 Linnacres Inc., 2013 (Box-folder 6.2)
  - CFR 1198 Duck Inn Group, LLC, 2013 (Box-folder 6.3)
  - CFR 1199 Johnson, Robert and Lenore, 2013 (Box-folder 6.4)
  - CFR 1200 Lieuallen, Donald, Robert and Penny, 2013 (Box-folder 6.5)
  - CFR 1201 Powers Ranch Co., 2013 (Box-folder 6.6)
  - CFR 1202 Walton, Joseph, 2013 (Box-folder 6.7)
  - CFR 1203 David and Doris Cruickshank Family Trust, 2013 (Box-folder 6.8)
  - CFR 1204 Reeder, Clinton and Karen, 2013 (Box-folder 6.9)
  - CFR 1205 Ebell, Mardelle, 2013 (Box-folder 6.01)
  - CFR 1206 Bacon, Lois, 2014 (Box-folder 6.11)
  - CFR 1207 Gastin, Ted, 2014 (Box-folder 6.12)
  - CFR 1208 Thompson, Larry and Moulds, Janet, 2014 (Box-folder 6.13)
  - CFR 1209 Jansen, Wilbur Peter, 2014 (Box-folder 6.14)
  - CFR 1210 Brewer, Joanne Emerson, 2014 (Box-folder 6.15)
  - CFR 1211 Kilkenny, John and Diane, 2014 (Box-folder 6.16)
  - CFR 1212 Plagmann, Terrill, 2014 (Box-folder 6.17)
  - CFR 1213 Landforce, Debora and Champeau, Donna, 2014 (Box-folder 6.18)
  - CFR 1214 Cheyne, Brent, 2015 (Box-folder 7.1)
  - CFR 1215 Falk, Aart and Charlene, 2015 (Box-folder 7.2)
  - CFR 1216 Moore, Janna and Steve and Falk, Aart and Charlene, 2015 (Box-folder 7.3)
  - CFR 1217 Evelyn and Tom Hynes Trust, 2015 (Box-folder 7.4)
  - CFR 1218 Fisher, Evelyn and Patterson, Katherine, 2015 (Box-folder 7.5)
  - CFR 1219 Finegan, Joseph and Jennifer, 2015 (Box-folder 7.6)
  - CFR 1220 Christensen, Hubert and Carolyn, 2015 (Box-folder 7.7)
  - CFR 1221 Harris, Greg and Bell, Richard, 2015 (Box-folder 7.8)
  - CFR 1222 Padget, Dale and Deanna, 2015 (Box-folder 7.9)
  - CFR 1223 Hall, Madeline and Fisher, Joseph, 2015 (Box-folder 7.01)
  - CFR 1224 Bingaman, Gregory, 2015 (Box-folder 7.11)
  - CFR 1225 Devenport, Ken and Earl, 2016 (Box-folder 8.01)
  - CFR 1226 Douglas P. Alley Family Trust, 2016 (Box-folder 8.02)
  - CFR 1227 Mills, Lois, 2016 (Box-folder 8.03)
  - CFR 1228 Grossen, David, 2016 (Box-folder 8.04)
  - CFR 1229 Carman Ranch LLC, 2016 (Box-folder 8.05)
  - CFR 1230 Omeg, Melvin and Linda, 2016 (Box-folder 8.06)
- Sesquicentennial Farm and Ranch Application Files, 2008-2016; Series 2
  Series 2 consists of Oregon Sesqucentennial Farm and Ranch applications for the years 2008 through the present. Applications and supporting materials such as property records and family history documents are submitted to the Century Farm and Ranch Program, part of the Oregon Farm Bureau, for recognition of family owning and working the same land for one hundred fifty years or more. Each application and supporting materials are individually foldered and arranged in chronological order by SFR (Sesquicentennial Farm and Ranch) number. One oversized 14 x 18 inch box holds oversized photos belonging to SFR 0011.
  - SFR 0001 Birdseye II, Victor Theodore, 2008 (Box-folder 9.1)
  - SFR 0002 Coon, Donald and Donna and Coon, Mike and Tami, 2008 (Box-folder 9.2)
  - SFR 0003 Ford Farms Inc., 2008 (Box-folder 9.3)
  - SFR 0004 Friedrich, Robert, 2008 (Box-folder 9.4)
  - SFR 0005 Herrling, Frankin, 2008 (Box-folder 9.5)
  - SFR 0006 Johns, Jack E., Vaughan, Eugene and Floyd and Gienger, Carol, 2008 (Box-folder 9.6)
  - SFR 0007 MacFarlane, William H., 2008 (Box-folder 9.7)
  - SFR 0008 McKay, Dean Arthur, 2008 (Box-folder 9.8)
  - SFR 0009 Martinak, Art and Joyce, 2008 (Box-folder 9.9)
  - SFR 0010 Rice, Richard, 2008 (Box-folder 9.10)
  - SFR 0011 Richardson, Dwane, 2008 (Box-folder 9.11)
  - SFR 0011 Richardson, Dwane. Oversized Photographs, 2008 (Box-folder 13.1)
  - SFR 0012 Scott, Guy and Mary Ann, 2008 (Box-folder 9.12)
  - SFR 0013 Vasconi, Ann and Davenport III, John, 2008 (Box-folder 9.13)
  - SFR 0014 Heater, James and Timothy, 2008 (Box-folder 9.14)
  - SFR 0015 Donald C. Goodrich and Eunice M. Goodrich Trusts, 2009 (Box-folder 9.15)
  - SFR 0016 Gray, Marian, 2009 (Box-folder 9.16)
  - SFR 0017 Hoyt, William, 2009 (Box-folder 9.17)
  - SFR 0018 Montgomery, Leland, 2009 (Box-folder 9.18)
  - SFR 0019 Owen, Rebecca, 2009 (Box-folder 9.19)
  - SFR 0020 Chrisman, Kenneth R., 2010 (Box-folder 10.1)
  - SFR 0021 Mitchell, Ralph and Pam, 2010 (Box-folder 10.2)
  - SFR 0022 Byron Scott Farms Inc., 2010 (Box-folder 10.3)
  - SFR 0023 Mader, Jackie and Charlotte, 2011 (Box-folder 10.4)
  - SFR 0024 McPhillips Farms Inc., 2012 (Box-folder 10.5)
  - SFR 0025 Mark Charles Talcott Trust, 2012 (Box-folder 10.6)
  - SFR 0026 Van Domelen, Vanessa, 2014 (Box-folder 10.7)
  - SFR 0027 Batchelder Farms LLC, 2014 (Box-folder 10.8)
  - SFR 0028 Moberg, Richard and Michelle, VanDehey, Mitchell and Cherie and Fox, Ryan and Kathy, 2014 (Box-folder 10.9)
  - SFR 0029 Flint, Harlan and Beverly, 2015 (Box-folder 10.10)
  - SFR 0030 Hemphill, Charles and Richard, 2015 (Box-folder 10.11)
  - SFR 0031 Adams, John W., 2015 (Box-folder 10.12)
  - SFR 0032 Smith, George and Alicia, 2015 (Box-folder 10.13)
  - SFR 0033 Lieuallen, A. Brooks, 2015 (Box-folder 10.14)
  - SFR 0034 Smith, Floyd and Betty Jo, 2016 (Box-folder 11.1)
  - SFR 0035 Zimmerman, Gordon, 2016 (Box-folder 11.2)
  - SFR 0036 Cox, Louise, 2016 (Box-folder 11.3)
  - SFR 0037 Ewing, Thomas and Zan, 2016 (Box-folder 11.4)
  - SFR 0038 Colson, Carolyn, 2016 (Box-folder 11.5)
- Administrative Materials and Awards Ceremonies, 2006-2016; Series 3
  Series 3 consists of materials generated for the annual Century and Sesquicentennial Farm and Ranch awards ceremony at the Oregon State Fair for the years 2006 through the present. Materials include fliers advertising the ceremony, lists of the awardees, the 2014 and 2015 newsletters, photograhs, and CDs of digital photos of the ceremony.
  - Award Ceremony, 2006 (Box-folder 12.1)
  - Award Ceremony, 2007 (Box-folder 12.2)
  - Award Ceremony, 2008 (Box-folder 12.3)
  - Award Ceremony, 2009 (Box-folder 12.4)
    Along with award ceremony materials, contains the book "Eating It Up in Eden: The Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Cookbook" by Richard Engeman.
  - Award Ceremony, 2010 (Box-folder 12.5)
  - Award Ceremony, 2011 (Box-folder 12.6)
  - Award Ceremony, 2012 (Box-folder 12.7)
  - Award Ceremony, 2013 (Box-folder 12.8)
  - Award Ceremony, 2014 (Box-folder 12.9)
  - Award Ceremony, 2015 (Box-folder 12.10)
    Along with award ceremony materials contains 2014 newsletter.
  - Award Ceremony, 2016 (Box-folder 12.11)
    Along with award ceremony materials contains 2015 newsletter.
- Century Farm and Ranch Database, 2016; Series 4
  The Century Farm and Ranch database is hosted by Oregon Explorer for the Oregon Century Farm and Ranch Program and provides information gathered from the award applications from 1958 to 2016 for Century and Sesquicentennial farms and ranches throughout Oregon. The database lists all the farms and ranches that have been accepted into the program since its inception in 1958. Data may include the historic and current acreage of the property, structures currently residing on the property, the economic use of the farm or ranch, and whether the property was part of a donation land claim. The database is updated annually and provides publically available data that can be downloaded. Database link:http://ocfrp.library.oregonstate.edu/public/farms.